# Danielle Albers Szafir

# University of Colorado Boulder

Homepage: http://www.danielleszafir.com

315 UCB Department of Information Science University of Colorado Boulder, CO 80309

**☎** 303.492.8532 ⋈ danielle.szafir@colorado.edu

## **Research Statement**

My research bridges data visualization and perception to drive the design of novel systems for analyzing large and complex datasets. I focus on expanding our knowledge of perception in order to evaluate how visualization design impacts users' abilities to accomplish their analytical goals. Through this process, I derive quantified insight into the role of perception in interpreting visualizations by gauging how real viewers in natural environments perceive encoded information. I use this knowledge to design systems and techniques that overcome scalability and interpretability limitations in existing designs. The resulting visualizations address research problems across a variety of domains, including genomics, proteomics, biochemistry, and the humanities.

# Professional Experience

2015-Present Founding Assistant Professor

Department of Information Science, University of Colorado Boulder

Affliate Appointments: Department of Computer Science, Institute of Cognitive Science

2010-2015 Research Assistant

Department of Computer Sciences, University of Wisconsin-Madison

2013 Research Intern

Tableau Software, Menlo Park, CA

2012 Software Development Intern

Google, Madison, WI

2009 Software Development Intern

Boston Scientific, CRM, Redmond, WA

2008–2009 Software Development Intern

Apptio, Bellevue, WA

## Education

2009-2015 Ph.D. in Computer Sciences

University of Wisconsin-Madison

Dissertation: "Utilizing Color for Perceptually-Driven Data Visualization."

Thesis Committee: Michael Gleicher, Steven Franconeri, Bilge Mutlu, Robert Roth, & Kevin Ponto.

Minor studies in perceptual psychology and art history.

2009-2011 Master of Science in Computer Sciences

University of Wisconsin-Madison

2007-2009 Bachelor of Science in Computer Science

University of Washington

NASA Space Grant Scholar, four-time Dean's List Member, graduated at age 20.

Minor in mathematics.

## **Honors & Awards**

2014	MERL Best Student Paper Award
	IS&T 22nd Color and Imaging Conference for "Adapting Color Difference for Design

2014 Invited Participant
Genres of Scholarly Knowledge Production 2014

# 2014 **Honorable Mention for Best Presentation**McPherson Eye Research Institute Symposium

## 2014 Andrew W. Mellon Workshop Grant Digital Humanities Research Network

# 2013 **Best SciVis Poster Award**IEEE VIS for "Lightness Constancy in Surface Visualization"

# 2013 Invited Participant IEEE VIS Doctoral Colloquium

2010–2012 **Research Fellow**BACTER Institute, University of Wisconsin-Madison

2007–2009 NASA Space Grant Scholar
NASA Space Grant, University of Washington Chapter

2007–2009 **Dean's List Member**University of Washington

## Publications

### Journal Publications<sup>1</sup>

A. Sarikaya, M. Gleicher, and **D. Albers Szafir**. "The Design of Visual Summaries." *IEEE Transactions of Visualization and Computer Graphics*, 2016. (under revision)

- **D. Albers Szafir**, D. Stuffer, Y. Sohail, and M. Gleicher. "TextDNA: Visualizing Word Usage Patterns with Configurable Colorfields." *Computer Graphics Forum*, 2016. In the Proceedings of the Eurographics Conference on Visualization (Acceptance Rate: 26%)
- **D. Albers Szafir**, S. Haroz, M. Gleicher, and S. Franconeri. "Four Types of Ensemble Coding for Data Visualizations." *Journal of Vision*, 16(11), 2016. (Impact Factor: 2.34)
- **D. Albers Szafir**, A. Sarikaya, and M. Gleicher. "Lightness Constancy in Surface Visualization." *IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics*, 2016 (to appear).
- A. Sarikaya, **D. Albers**, J. Mitchell, and M. Gleicher. "Visualizing Validation of Protein Surface Classifiers." *Computer Graphics Forum*, 33(3), 2014. In the Proceedings of the Eurographics Conference on Visualization. (Acceptance Rate: 25%)
- **D. Albers**, C. Dewey, and M. Gleicher. "Sequence Surveyor: Leveraging Overview for Scalable Genomic Alignment Visualization." *IEEE Transactions of Visualization and Computer Graphics*, 17(5), 2011. In the Proceedings of the IEEE Information Visualization Conference. (Acceptance Rate: 25%)
- M. Gleicher, **D. Albers**, R. Walker, I. Jusufi, C. Hansen, and J. Roberts. "Visual Comparison for Information Visualization." *Information Visualization*, 10(4), 2011. (Impact Factor: 0.89)

Note that IEEE Information Visualization conference proceedings are published as an issue of IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, and EuroVis conference proceedings are published as an issue of Computer Graphics Forum.

## Refereed Conference Publications<sup>2</sup>

- **D. Albers Szafir**, M. Stone, and M. Gleicher. "Adapting Color Difference for Design." *IS&T 22nd Color and Imaging Conference*, 2014. [Best Paper Award]
- M. Stone, **D. Albers Szafir**, and V. Setlur. "An Engineering Model for Color Discriminability as a Function of Size." *IS&T 22nd Color and Imaging Conference*, 2014.
- **D. Albers**, M. Correll, and M. Gleicher. "Task-Driven Evaluation of Aggregation in Time Series Visualization." *Proceedings of the 2014 Annual Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI)*, 2014. (Acceptance Rate: 23%)
- M. Correll, **D. Albers**, S. Franconeri, and M. Gleicher. "Comparing Averages in Time Series Data." *Proceedings of the 2012 Annual Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI)*, 2012. (Acceptance Rate: 23%)

## **Refereed Abstracts**

- D. Albers Szafir and M. Gleicher. "Visualization-Aware Color Design." EuroVis, 2016.
- **D. Albers**, M. Correll, M. Gleicher, and S. Franconeri. "Ensemble Processing of Color and Shape: Beyond Mean Judgments." *Journal of Vision*, 14(9), 2014.
- **D. Albers**, A. Sarikaya, and M. Gleicher. "Lightness Constancy in Surface Visualization." *Poster Abstracts of IEEE VIS*, 2013. [Best Poster Award]
- A. Sarikaya, **D. Albers**, and M. Gleicher. "Understanding Performance of Protein Structural Classifiers." *Poster Abstracts of IEEE VIS*, 2013.
- **D. Albers**, C. Dewey, and M. Gleicher. "Sequence Surveyor: Leveraging Overview for Large-Scale Genomic Alignment Visualization." *Proceedings of VizBi 2011: Visualizing Biological Data*, 2011.
- **D. Albers** and M. Gleicher. "Poster: Perceptual Principles for Scalable Sequence Alignment Visualization." 2010 IEEE Information Visualization Poster Proceedings, 2010.
- **D. Albers** and M. Gleicher. "Perceptual Principles for Scalable Sequence Alignment Visualization." *Proceedings of the 7th Symposium on Applied Perception in Graphics and Visualization*, 2010.

## **Workshops & Colloquia**

- **D. Albers Szafir** & D. Szafir. "Cognitive Load in Visualization: Myths and Misconceptions." *Creation, Curation, Critique and Conditioning of Principles and Guidelines in Visualization (C4PGV).* 2016.
- **D. Albers Szafir**. "Considering Connectivity for Visualization Design." *Human-Computer Interaction Consortium (HCIC)*. 2016.
- **D. Albers Szafir**. "Using Graphical Perception to Drive Visualization Design." *Visualization Summer Camp.* 2016.
- E. Alexander and **D. Albers Szafir**. "D3.js: Javascript for Data Visualization." Second Annual Digital Humanities+Art Symposium: Going Public. 2015.
- M. Correll, E. Alexander, **D. Albers Szafir**, A. Sarikaya, and M. Gleicher. "Navigating Reductionism and Holism in Evaluation." *BELIV '14: Beyond Time and Errors—Novel Evaluation Methods for Visualization*, 2014.
- D. Albers Szafir. "Thinking with Data." Digital Humanities Research Network, 2014.

Note that conferences are a primary publication venue in Computer & Information Sciences.

- **D. Albers**. "Perceptually Informed Scalable Sequence Comparison." *IEEE VIS Doctoral Colloquium*, 2013.
- **D. Albers** and Michael Gleicher. "Seeing Double: Crowdsourced Models of Color Discrimination." *Mid-graph: Midwest Graphics Workshop*, 2012.

### **Theses & Dissertations**

**D. Albers Szafir**. "Utilizing Color for Perceptually-Driven Data Visualization." *University of Wisconsin-Madison*, 2015.

## **Invited Talks**

- "Perceptually-Driven Visualization of Complex Data." Rochester Institute of Technology, Rochester, New York, 2015.
- "Perceptually-Driven Visualization of Complex Data." *Digital Arts Colloquium*, University of Iowa, Iowa City, Iowa, 2015.
- "Perceptually-Driven Visualization of Complex Data." Data @ ASU, Arizona State University, Tempe, Arizona, 2015.
- "Perceptually-Driven Visualization of Complex Data." *Information Science Seminar*, University of Colorado Boulder, Boulder, Colorado, 2015.
- "Color & Size." Developer's Seminar. Tableau Software, Palo Alto, CA (joint work w. Maureen Stone and Vidya Setlur).
- "Informing Visualization in the Humanities through Perception and Genomics." *Genres of Scholarly Knowledge Production*, Umeå University, Umeå, Sweden, 2014.

## **Intramural Talks & Lectures**

- "Model-View-Controller." Guest Lecture, ATLS 5419: Introduction to Virtual Reality, University of Colorado Boulder, 2016.
- "An Introduction to Data Visualization." Science Learner's Lunch, University of Colorado Boulder, 2015.
- "Driving Scalable Visualization with Perception." *Guest Lecture, CSCI 4830: Big Data & HCI*, University of Colorado Boulder, 2015.
- "Perceptually-Driven Information Visualization." *CU Libraries Research Seminar*, University of Colorado Boulder, 2015.
- "The Graphics Pipeline." Guest Lecture, ATLS 5419: Introduction to Virtual Reality, University of Colorado Boulder, 2015.
- "Introduction to Three.js." Guest Lecture, ATLS 5419: Introduction to Virtual Reality, University of Colorado Boulder, 2015.
- "Perceptually-Driven Information Visualization." *Institute of Cognitive Science Seminar*, University of Colorado Boulder, 2015.
- "Perceptually-Driven Information Visualization." *Human-Centered Computing Seminar*, University of Colorado Boulder. 2015.
- "Interaction in Visualization." *Guest Lecture, CS 838: Visualization*, University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, Wisconsin, 2015.

"Insights at a Glance: Visualization at UW-Madison." *MERI at a Glance*, McPherson Eye Research Institute, Madison, Wisconsin, 2014.

"Color for Computer Graphics." *Guest Lecture, CS 559: Computer Graphics*, University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, Wisconsin, 2014.

"Image Compression." *Guest Lecture, CS 559: Computer Graphics*, University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, Wisconsin, 2014.

"Perceptually-Driven Sequence Visualization." Guest Lecture, CS 838: Visualization, University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, Wisconsin, 2012.

# Funding

#### **Grants**

(Under Review) \$174,925: NSF CRII. "Data-Driven Automation of Color Encodings for Data Visualization," 2016 (PI: D. Albers Szafir).

(Under Review) \$359,424: Air Force Young Investigators Program. "Enabling Man-Machine Collaboration in Scalable Analytics," 2016 (Pl. D. Albers Szafir).

\$30,000: University of Colorado Boulder Innovative Seed Grant. "FieldView: Using Mobile Devices to Blend Data Collection and Analysis for Field Research," 2016 (PI: D. Albers Szafir).

\$7,500: Andrew W. Mellon Workshop Grant. "Digital Humanities Research Network," 2014.

## **Fellowships**

IEEE VIS Doctoral Colloquium, 2013.

BACTER Research Fellowship. Department of Energy's Institute for Bringing Computational Techniques to Energy Research (BACTER Institute) at the University of Wisconsin-Madison, 2010-2012.

NASA Space Grant Fellowship, 2007-2009.

# **Teaching**

2016 Co-Instructor

INFO 1201: Computational Reasoning I, University of Colorado Boulder Co-designed new course in introductory computer programming delivered to 135 undergraduates.

2009 Teaching Assistant

Human-Computer Interaction, University of Wisconsin-Madison

2009 Laboratory Instructor

Introduction to Programming, University of Wisconsin-Madison Mean Instructor Rating: 4.58/5.00

2008-2009 Mathematics and English Instructor

Kumon of Redmond, Redmond, WA

# Mentorship & Advising

## **Thesis Committee Membership**

2016 **Brett Roads**, Ph.D. Thesis, Advisor: Michael Mozer

The Design of Efficient Training and Decision-Support Systems for Visual Categorization

Department of Computer Science, University of Colorado Boulder

2015 **Khalid Alharbi**, Ph.D. Thesis, Advisor: Tom Yeh A Deep and Longitudinal Approach to Mining Mobile Applications Department of Computer Science, University of Colorado Boulder

#### Ph.D. Students

2016 **Michael Iuzzolino (w. Daniel Szafir)**University of Colorado Boulder

2016 **Dasha Pruss (w. Michael Paul)**University of Colorado Boulder

2016 **Matthew Whitlock**University of Colorado Boulder

## **Masters Students**

## 2016 Praveen Devaraj (as Thesis Committee Chair)

Using Visualization to Enable Human-Machine Collaboration University of Colorado Boulder

2016 Yogitha Madhasu

Visual Analytics for Inductive Scholarship University of Colorado Boulder

2016 Shashidhar Prabhu

Visualizing Data in the Internet of Things University of Colorado Boulder

## **Undergraduate Students**

#### 2016 Tetsumichi Umada

Using Visualization to Enable Human-Machine Collaboration University of Colorado Boulder

## 2016 Ryan Mustari

Statistically Controlled Synthetic Data Generation University of Colorado Boulder

## 2016 Alex Thompson

Visualizing Data in Augmented Reality University of Colorado Boulder

## 2016 Connor Mcguinness (now at Uber)

Color Encodings for Ordinal Data University of Colorado Boulder

## 2015 Yusef Suhail

Web-based N-Grams Visualization with TextDNA University of Wisconsin-Madison

#### 2014 Andrew Hermus

Scalable Visualization for Text Analytics (w. Eric Alexander) University of Wisconsin-Madison

## 2013 Benjamin Reddersen

Rendering Techniques for Molecular Surface Visualization University of Wisconsin-Madison

## Professional Activities & Service

## **Professional Outreach**

2016 Aspirations in Computing Colorado Affiliate Committee
National Center for Women in Technology

#### 2010-2015 **ACM-W Mentor**

Department of Computer Sciences, University of Wisconsin-Madison

## 2009 Majors Fair Representative

Department of Computer Sciences, University of Wisconsin-Madison

## 2009 **Department Guide**

Department of Computer Sciences, University of Washington

## **University Service**

# 2016 **Co-Chair, Digital Humanities Certificate Committee**University of Colorado Boulder

## 2016 External Programs Coordinator

Department of Information Science, University of Colorado Boulder

## 2016 Faculty Search Committee

Leeds School of Business, University of Colorado Boulder

## 2015 - 2016 Graduate Program Committee

Department of Information Science, University of Colorado Boulder

## 2015 - 2016 Graduate Program Committee

Department of Computer Science, University of Colorado Boulder

## 2015-2016 Community and Diversity Committee

College of Media, Communication, and Information, University of Colorado Boulder

## 2015-2016 Research Data Advisory Committee

University of Colorado Boulder

#### 2015 Curriculum Committee

Department of Information Science, University of Colorado Boulder

## 2015 Faculty Search Committee

Department of Information Science, University of Colorado Boulder

# 2014-2015 Digital Humanities Research Network Founding Member & Coordinator

University of Wisconsin-Madison

## 2012–2015 Visualization Reading Group Founder & Coordinator

University of Wisconsin-Madison

## 2015 **Organizing Committee Member**

University of Wisconsin-Madison Digital Humanities+Art Symposium

## **Program Committees & Referee Service**

2014–2016 **Program Committee Member** 

BioVis: Symposium on Biological Data Visualization

2016 **Program Committee Member** 

LDAV: IEEE Symposium on Large Data Analysis and Visualization

2013-2016 **Reviewer** 

IEEE Information Visualization Special Recognition: 2014, 2015

2016 Reviewer

LDAV: IEEE Symposium on Large Data Analysis and Visualization

2013-2016 Reviewer

BioVis: Symposium on Biological Data Visualization

2016 Reviewer

IEEE RO-MAN: IEEE Conference on Robot and Human Interactive Communication

2014, 2016 Reviewer

BMC Medical Informatics and Decision Making

2015-2016 **Reviewer** 

IEEE Visual Analytics Science and Technology (VAST)

2016 Reviewer

ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI)

Special Recognition: 2016

2016 Reviewer

Eurographics Conference on Visualization

2015 Reviewer Ad Hoc

National Science Foundation Information Integration and Informatics (III)

2015 Reviewer

Informatics

2015 Reviewer

Transactions on Cartography and Geographic Information Science

# **Professional & Academic Memberships**

2010-Present ACM Member

2014-2015 IS&T Student Member

2012-2015 WHCI+D Member

2010-2015 IEEE Student Member

2008-Present Sigma Alpha Lambda Honor Society Member

2008-Present Phi Theta Kappa International Honor Society Member

## **Volunteer Positions**

2009-2014 **Web Manager** 

University of Wisconsin-Madison Women's Hockey Club

## 2011-2012 Assistant Practice Coach

Wisconsin Timberwolves Special Needs Hockey Team

#### 2010 GRE Tutor

University of Wisconsin-Madison

## 2007-2008 Ice Hockey Officiating Mentor

Cascade Hockey Officiating Association

## **Professional References**

## Michael Gleicher, Professor

Department of Computer Sciences University of Wisconsin-Madison 1210 W. Dayton Street Madison, WI 53706 gleicher@cs.wisc.edu

## Maureen Stone, Research Scientist

Tableau Software 837 N. 34th Street, Suite 200 Seattle, WA 98103 mstone@tableausoftware.com

## Steven Franconeri, Associate Professor

Department of Psychology Northwestern University Swift Hall 102, 2029 Sheridan Road Evanston, IL 60208 franconeri@northwestern.edu

## **Kevin Ponto, Assistant Professor**

Design Studies Department University of Wisconsin-Madison 330 N. Orchard Street Madison, WI 53715 kbponto@wisc.edu